<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>By the King. Whereas the custody and safe keeping of our seuerall counties and shires of our realme of England, are by our ancient common lawes committed to seuerall shiriffes  ...</title>
            <title>Proclamations. 1605-11-19</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1603-1625 : James I)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1605</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 5 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A73962</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 8386</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S123965</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99898324</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99898324</idno>
            <idno type="VID">173539</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A73962)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 173539)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2062:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>By the King. Whereas the custody and safe keeping of our seuerall counties and shires of our realme of England, are by our ancient common lawes committed to seuerall shiriffes  ...</title>
                  <title>Proclamations. 1605-11-19</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1603-1625 : James I)</author>
                  <author>James I, King of England, 1566-1625.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>2 sheets (versos blank)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>by Robert Barker, printer to the Kings most excellent Maiestie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Dom. 1605]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title from caption title and opening lines of text.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Dated at end: Giuen at our lapace of Westminster, the nineteenth day of Nouember, in the third yeere of our reigne of Great Britaine, France and Ireland.</note>
                  <note>Arms 9; Steele notation: se- committed 2) or escape.</note>
                  <note>Authorizing sheriffs to pursue rebels across county borders -- STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Outlaws --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  James I, 1603-1625 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Broadsides --  England</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="royal_proclamation">
            <pb facs="tcp:173539:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 40 -->
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>royal blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> By the King.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas the cuſtody and ſafe keeping of our</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall Counties and Shires of our Realme of England, are by our ancient Commonlawes committed to ſeuerall Shiriffes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ancient Conſeruators of the Peace, and Miniſters of Iuſtice within the ſame, who by force of their Offices may aſſemble, and take the power and ſtrength of our ſayd Counties and Shires committed to their charge, not onely for the due execution of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, but alſo for the preſeruation of our Peace, and the ſpeedy and timely diſſolution and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing of all Inſurrections, Rebellions, outragious Riots, Routes, and other exorbitant and vnlawfull aſſemblies, to the end that ſuch dangerous attempts might bee ſuppreſſed in their beginnings, and our louing Subiects liue and exerciſe their ſeueral vocations in al peace and plentie; The good effect of the execution of which Lawes hath well appeared, in that the moſt deteſtable and diabolicall Rebellion of <hi>Percy</hi> and his Complices in our Counties of <hi>Warwicke, Worceſter,</hi> and <hi>Stafford,</hi> (that had bene ſo ſecretly contriued, and ſo long in hatching) was by the peaceable Miniſters of our Lawes, and by due execution of their Offices, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any extraordinary power or forces, moſt loyally, reſolutely, and ſpeedily ſuppreſſed: And whereas ſome queſtion or ſcruple hath bene (as wee are enformed) mooued amongſt ſome of the vulgar, Whether any of our Sheriffes may, with the Power of their ſeuerall Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties or Shires, in purſuit of Rebels and Traitours, follow them into any other County, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit by the Lawes of this Realme, Sheriffes, as it falleth out in dayly experience, in priuate caſes betweene party and party (matters of no ſuch eminent and publike danger and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence as this is) iuſtly and lawfully doe the like, whereof Wee preſume few or none can be ignorant: Yet Wee meaning to giue ſatiſfaction to all, doe hereby publiſh and declare, That ſuch purſuit of Rebels and Traitors into other Counties, is not onely in ſuch caſes lawfull and iuſtifiable, But, that if any of our Subiects being thereunto required by any of our Sheriffes, ſhall not follow and aſſiſt them in ſuch purſuit, that they are to bee ſeuerely and ſharpely puniſhed for their high contempt and offence in that behalfe.</p>
            <p>But if in ſuch purſuite the Sheriffe of the ſame Countie or Shire (whereunto ſuch Rebels or Traytors ſhal flye or eſcape) ſhall alſo come with the power of his Countie before ſuch Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels or Traytors bee apprehended or ſuppreſſed, Then the Sheriffe ſo purſuing from any
<pb facs="tcp:173539:2"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 41 -->other Countie or Shire ſhall aſſiſt and ioyne with the Sheriffe in his proper Countie or Shire, for the apprehenſion or ſuppreſſing of ſuch Rebels and Traitors. And it ſuch Rebels or Traytors ſhall flie or eſcape into any houſe or other place of ſtrength and defence, and ſhall not yeeld themſelues being thereunto required by the Sheriffe or any of his companie that ſo ſhall purſue them, but obſtinately and wilfully make reſiſtance, That then it ſhall be lawfull for euery ſuch Sheriffe ſo purſuing with ſuch power and ſtrength, as he ſhall col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, or ſhall aſſiſt him, to beate downe, burne, or otherwiſe waſt any ſuch houſe or place of defence for the better apprehenſion or ſuppreſſing of ſuch Rebels and Traytors. And albeit we deſire that ſuch induſtrie and care may be taken, as that ſuch offendors may be apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded aliue, Yet wee let it be knowen, that if otherwiſe through their rebellious obſtinacy and reſiſtance, ſuch Rebellion cannot be ſuppreſſed; That it ſhall be lawfull and iuſtifiable in thoſe caſes of neceſſitie, for the Sheriffe and his Company aſſiſting him, to kill and deſtroy ſuch Traytors and Rebels. And as the faithfull endeuours of our louing Subiects with ſuch alacrity as they haue ſhewed in this late Rebellion, is very acceptable vnto vs; So if in any ſuch caſe any perſon or perſons ſhall vnder pretence of our publique ſeruice, maliciouſly and vniuſtly ſeeke to reuenge any priuate quarrell, We let them know that they ſhall not eſcape without ſeuere and condigne puniſhments according to their demerits in that behalfe.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Giuen at our Palace of Weſtminſter, <date>the nineteenth day of Nouember, in the third yeereof our Reigne of <hi>Great Britaine, France</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <lb/>
God ſaue the King.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Imprinted at London by Robert Barker, Printer to the Kings moſt Excellent Maieſtie.</p>
            <p>ANNO DOM. 1605.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:173539:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 42 -->
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
